Guide to the William A. Price Papers TAM.398
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Box 7, 1940s-2000s
  This box mostly contains an assortment of collected reports, correspondence, news and scholarly articles (some written by Price), and other materials from a variety of sources collected by Price relating to the WSURA, racial discrimination in city planning, the urbanization of NYC, relocation, and public housing as a general issue. An April 1979 draft of the WSURA Fifth Amended Renewal Plan by HPD is also included. The activities of CONTINUE from the mid-1970s to mid-1980s and the United Independent-Socialist Party during the 1950s are also particularly well-documented.
  To a lesser extent, correspondence, newsletters, minutes, reports, legal documents, and other materials relate specifically to the New York Council to Abolish the House Un-American Activities Committee, UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc. vs. Price, UTA, and SBNC. Subject files created by the the Committee of First Amendment Defendants are also present, which provide information on the individual cases of people who invoked the First Amendment when they were imprisoned on charges of association with the Communist Party and/or civil rights organizations. There is also some personal correspondence, photographs, and ephemera, including materials dating back to Price's World War II service. Many photographs and negatives are unidentified, though some appear to be of the "L" Club in Montclair and Price's time on Fire Island.
- Box 8, 1950s-1990s
  Most of the box consists of materials generated by the UTA, UTA Ad Hoc Committee, HPD, Community Board #7, SBNC, the NYC Housing Authority, Community Action, Inc., and various low-rent housing groups. Genres of materials include legal documents (particularly pertaining to UTA/MHA vs. UTA Ad Hoc); UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc. by-laws; financial documents; flyers and other publicity materials; newsletters; news clippings; photographs; minutes; correspondence and memoranda; and proposals and reports. Some photographs, flyers, and other visual materials appear to have been collected for a slideshow. The materials document the debates over the WSURA in particular and urban development in general. There is also an unpublished housing study published by the City Planning Commission (CPC).
  To a lesser extent, the box contains subject files of mostly news clippings and correspondence on individual First Amendment cases, compiled by the the Committee of First Amendment Defendants. Similarly, there are writings and other materials in opposition to HUAC and a copy of Price's testimony before the Senate Internal Security Subcommittee. Additionally, there are photographs from an Independent-Socialist Party meeting and proposals and other materials generated by the Committee for Independent Political Action (CIPA) and other socialist or otherwise left-wing groups. Materials regarding racism in the U.S. and materials that document the civil rights movement are particularly prevalent, including those generated by the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee and the Southern Conference Educational Fund (SCEF).
  Also included are a small number of materials on the Newsmen's Commission to Investigate the Murder of George Polk; National Guardian memoranda; a subject file on poverty (including materials generated by the People's War Council Against Poverty); photographs from Cuba, some dating to the 1950s; and unidentified photographs.
- Box 9, 1950s-2000s
  This box is mainly comprised of by-laws, minutes, correspondence and memoranda, newsletters, statements, and other materials on the WSURA and low-rent housing The materials were generated by the UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc., UTA Ad Hoc Committee, CONTINUE, SBNC, HPD, National Low Incoming Housing Coalition, and other government or housing activist groups.
  The box also contains a series of articles apparently compiled for a conference on Cuba; reports, press releases, speeches, and other materials created by the Progressive Party, many regarding Eisenhower's election and presidency; and news clippings and legal documents pertaining to the Price vs. Kearney "Squad 47" wire tapping case. Subject files on the Trenton Six and the 1960s political climate consisting of news clippings, official statements, correspondence, press releases, and other materials, generated by various civil rights and left-wing political action groups (especially the Committee for Independent Political Action), are also present. There are photographs of unidentified buildings, meetings, and demonstrations, presumably of the WSURA and housing rights groups, and leaflets on civil rights, politics, and public welfare in Mississippi.
- Box 10, 1959-1965
  Scope and Contents
  This box contains materials concerning the First Amendment, Congressional anti-communist inquisition, and the civil rights movement as it relates to the Communist Party, USA. Organizations documented include the National Committee to Abolish HUAC (and the group's New York Council) and the Chicago Committee to Defend the Bill of Rights. Materials in this box include correspondence, memoranda, meeting notes, press releases, flyers and other ephemera, and newspaper clippings and small press publications.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Repository permission is required for access. Please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, 212-998-2630.
- Box 11, 1950s-1960s
  This box is mainly comprised of subject files on First Amendment cases compiled by the Committee of First Amendment Defendants, consisting mostly of news clippings and correspondence. The topics of the subject files are individuals accused of having affiliation with the Communist Party or suspected Communist-affiliated groups like the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Many of the subject files pertain to Price's experience with the Senate Internal Security Subcommittee. In addition to the subject files, there are publicity and organizing materials related to the opposition of HUAC and other Congressional inquisitorial committees.
  Correspondence, flyers, and press releases generated by the United Independent-Socialist Campaign Committee, as well as news clippings on the party and other topics in leftist politics, appear to have been compiled by Price for inclusion in a scrapbook.
- Box 12, 1940s-1970s
  This box pertains to opposition to HUAC and other forms of Congressional anti-communist inquisition. It contains subject files on First Amendment cases compiled by the Committee of First Amendment Defendants; notes, minutes, correspondence, flyers, and other materials created by NCAHUAC and the group's New York Council; and government documents and clippings related to Price's testimony before the Senate Internal Security Subcommittee (including a copy of his testimony).
  To a lesser extent, this box contains materials related to the civil rights movement, including newsletters, flyers, and correspondence generated by the Southern Conference Educational Fund (SCEF), as well as subject files on poverty and politically organizing poor Caucasian people.
- Box 13, 1960s-1990s
  This box mostly contains memoranda and correspondence created by the Executive Board of the New York Council to Abolish HUAC, as well as official statements, flyers, and correspondence generated by the National Committee to Abolish HUAC, the organization's New York Council, and the organization's other groups. The box also consists of correspondence with Frank Wilkinson of the Committee of First Amendment Defendants (CFAD); a subject file on linguistics in the South as it pertains to the education of African American students; a subject files of mostly news clippings on the civil rights movement as it relates to the Communist Party, USA; and press releases, speeches, and news clippings related to the politics of the Communist Party, USA and the Communist Party of New York State during the 1960s.
  To a lesser extent, there is an assortment of correspondence from SCEF, the National Guardian, NCAHUAC, and other groups and individuals, as well as news clippings on a variety of topics. There is also a small amount of information on renovations to Price's apartment, housing and human rights in Cuba, and Price's health.
- Box 14, circa 1960s
  Reel-to-reel tapes, mostly of civil rights groups and meetings
- Box 15, circa 1960s
- Box 16, 1960s-2000s
  The box is mostly comprised of agendas and minutes, reports, factsheets, flyers, memoranda and correspondence, news clippings, and other materials generated by or pertaining to the UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc., the Urban Homesteading Assistance Board (UHAB), SBNC, Community Action, Inc., and various housing rights groups, as well as the federal and New York City governments. Topics documented include the UTA/MHA proposal; disputes over rent, with particular emphasis on the UTA Ad Hoc Committee's proposal to add 2,500 units of low- and moderate-income housing; the indirect displacement of Penn Yards and urban dislocation more broadly; the demonstration against the Trinity Episcopal School Corporation and its attempts to block the construction of low-income housing; the Homefront campaign; and the development of the WSURA in general. There are also legal documents from Hudgins/CONTINUE vs. Koch/UTA, UTA Ad Hoc vs. Rafael M. Pantoja, Jr., UTA/MHA vs. Danilo Fernandez, and other cases, as well as a report on housing, race/ethnicity, and income in NYC by the Community Service Society.
  Price's other areas of interest are documented via materials on First Amendment cases; lecture notes and syllabi for classes on Community Development and Understanding Human Interaction and Behavior taught by Price at the School of Contemporary Studies, Brooklyn College; a subject file on race and intelligence; and printed ephemera on a variety of topics.
- Box 17, 1940s-1990s
  This box contains memoranda and correspondence, bylaws, legal documents, reports and proposals, flyers, notes, and other materials generated by or pertaining to the activities of UTA, UTA's Tenant Dignity Committee, SBNC and its Ad Hoc Committee for the 2,5000 Units, the Committee for Independent Political Action (CIPA), Community Action, Inc., and other community groups. The general topic of the box is development of the Upper West Side and low-income housing in the WSURA, but the box also specifically covers a variety of subjects, including Operation Move-In's 1970 negotiations with NYC's Housing and Development Administration; information on income rates in NYC; UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc. vs. Price; creating a historic district in the Upper West Side; the Fifth Amendment to the WSURA plan; race as it relates to the housing movement; the UTA/MHA proposal; mortgages; housing for senior citizens; the Cooper Square Urban Renewal Area; the Brooke Amendment; single room occupancy housing; Sites 30, 32, and 46; and Hudgins/CONTINUE vs. Koch/UTA. There are also materials generated by the local and U.S. government, including reports and guidelines authored by the NYC, NY county, and federal government on the in rem housing program, the future of housing in NYC, private management of low-rent public housing, and other topics; Community Board #7 resolutions, correspondence, and other materials on the Department of City's Planning's inclusionary zonings proposal in the 1980s; and U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development pamphlets and other printed ephemera on a variety of topics. There are also news clippings on a number of housing-related issues, including Roger Starr's "planned shrinkage" of the South Bronx.
  To a lesser extent, the box contains materials created by the Citywide Intergroup Coalition of NYC's Commission on Human Rights; W.E.B. DuBois speeches; a subject file of news clippings and reports on racism; and a subject file of mostly news clippings on criticism of the press and alleged examples of the press's biases.
- Box 18, 1940s-1990s
  This box contains news releases, flyers, agendas and minutes, by-laws, memoranda and correspondence, flyers, petitions, press releases, and news clippings pertaining to urban renewal in the WSURA, particularly debates over increased rents and the fight for low-income housing. Most materials were generated by the UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc., UTA Ad Hoc, the Coalition to Replan the West Side Urban Renewal Area, SBNC, Community Board #7, HPD/DAMP, and, to a lesser extent, the Little Old New York Citizen's Committee, Homefront, UHAB, the Community Service Society of New York, and Operation Move-In. Other, more specific topics documented include zoning; the rehabilitation or status of specific sites in the WSURA; the UTA/MHA proposal (including the UTA/MHA guide and handbook); the tenant interim lease (TIL) program; the Dorothy Smith eviction case; and the Fifth Amendment to the WSURA plan. There are also lengthy reports on "West Side Futures," regarding the infrastructure and demographics of the Upper West Side, and on creating low-income housing in New York, as well as legal documents pertaining to Hudgins/CONTINUE vs. Koch/UTA, UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc. vs. Price, UTA Ad Hoc vs. UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc., and the "Squad 47" wiretapping cases.
  To a much lesser extent, there are materials related to the civil rights movement and racism in the armed services, Price's appearance before the Senate Internal Security Subcommittee, the shared house on Fire Island, and Price's work for the National Guardian.
- Box 19, 1960s-1990s
  The majority of this box relates to the activities of the Stryker's Bay Neighborhood Council (SBNC). The box is comprised of reports and correspondence of the SBNC Housing Committee; agendas and minutes, correspondence, notes, reports, and publications created by the general SBNC and some of its subcommittees related to the WSURA; and legal documents pertaining to SBNC vs. NYC (Site 30 case). There are also reports, newsletters, and flyers and other publicity materials created by SBNC and the Site #30 Coalition regarding the groups' opposition to building a high-rise luxury apartment on the site.
  Other materials in the box were mostly created by to relate to the UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc. and/or the WSURA. These materials, which include by-laws, minutes, correspondence, news clippings, and other materials, pertain to the UTA/MHA proposal, resolutions regarding specific sites, HPD's Community Management contract with UTA, the Fifth Amendment to the WSURA Plan, Section #8, and other topics. There is also a subject file on urban renewal in other cities.
- Box 20, 1960s-1990s
  This box relates to housing debates over the WSURA. Most of the newsletters, memoranda and correspondence, flyers, and other materials were generated by UTA, UTA Ad Hoc, SBNC, and the Coalition to Replan the West Side Urban Renewal Area. Topics documented include the notion of racial "tipping points;" Site 30; the demonstrations against Trinity School for its opposition to low-income housing; and the UTA vs. UTA Ad Hoc dispute. There are also HPD community consultant contracts and an academic article on tenant organizations and the passage of the 1920 New York State emergency rent laws.
- Box 21, 1960s-2000s
  This box contains news clippings, memoranda and correspondence, legal documents, proposals and reports, flyers, factsheets, agendas and minutes, newsletters, by-laws, petitions, and other materials related to the efforts of community organizations regarding the WSURA. Many of the materials were generated by or pertain to UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc., UTA Ad Hoc, UTA's Tenant Dignity Committee, Community Board #7, SBNC, HPD/DAMP, UHAB, the Coalition to Replan the West Side Urban Renewal Area, Homefront, the Coalition of West Side Urban Renewal Area Community groups, and other community groups and government agencies. Materials pertain to the UTA/MHA-HDFC, Inc. and UTA Ad Hoc dispute, specifically as it relates to tenants of Site 46; the internal governance of UTA; the Fifth Amendment to the WSURA plan; the Tenant Interim Lease (TIL) program; Section 8; the details of renovation plans; and general resistance to the city's urban renewal plans for the WSURA and the struggle for more tenant control. There is also an undated copy of a Section 8 Housing Inspection Manual and an undated summary of the final WSURA plan, as well as reports on "white flight" and the future of school desegregation; problems among NYC-owned and former City-owned residential buildings; and housing abandonment in NYC. An inventory of the contents of a folder of news clippings is included within the folder.
- Box 22, 1980s
  Price's Fire Island journals
- Unprocessed Materials (Box OS004, Folder 1)